Gianmaria Del Monte

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Geneva - Switzerland

 ¶ +41 078 225 24 27

 | ■ gianmaria.del.monte@cern.ch

 | ■ github.com/gmgigi96

in linkedin.com/in/gianmaria-del-monte-81575b162



Personal Profile

Diligent Software Engineer with passion of designing and developing highly scalable software systems. Excellent attention to details and problem solving, with an innate ability to learn and master new technologies. Experience in software development's life cycle, including designing, coding, testing, delivery and maintenance. Keen to use my skills to push the frontiers of science and technology.

Education

MEDILS Split, Croatia

Thematic CERN School of Computing

• Held on Security of research computing infrastructures

Rome Tre University Rome, Italy

M.Sc. in Computer Engineering

2019 - 2020 • Thesis title: Scaling blockchains without giving up decentralization and security

- Thesis supervisor: Prof. Maurizio Pizzonia
- · Final mark: 110/110 with honors

Rome Tre University Rome, Italy

B.Sc. in Computer Engineering 2016 - 2018

- Thesis title: Implementation of an efficient protocol for data integrity on Cloud
- Thesis supervisor: Prof. Maurizio Pizzonia
- · Final mark: 110/110 with honors

Work Experience

CERN Geneva, Switzerland

Software Engineer

Jan 2021 - Present

- · Proactively support and maintain the CERNBox software ecosystem to provide a highly reliable service for more than 37K users, holding 18PB
- · Design, implementation and deployment of a new backup system for CERNBox/cephfs (24/7, 600M daily file ingest)
- · Engagement with the open source community (Reva) to provide various bug-fixes and major enhancements (Lock APIs, federated shares)
- Ensuring day-to-day operational activities are carried out in a timely and reliable way
- · Supervision of a summer student to implement self-restore functionalities to address user community demand
- · Coordination among other team members of successful delivery of service improvements, specially on the server side
- Support CERN IT Security Team as second line member to ensure Organization security
- Technical Skills: Go, Python, CentOS, Puppet, Bash, Git, MySQL, gRPC, REST APIs, EOS, distributed systems

Roma Tre University Rome, Italy

Teaching assistant Nov 2018 - Jul 2020

• Technical Skills: Java, C, data structures and algorithms

· Teaching assistant for Fundamentals of Computer Science course for the bachelor degree in Computer Engineering

Roma Tre University

Software Engineer Oct 2019 - Nov 2019

• Designed and implemented a mobile app that streamlines every aspect of student life at Roma Tre University, like booking a spot in the library, scheduling exams and real-time notifications about lecture delays and cancellations

• Technical Skills: Java, Android

Skills_

Programming Java, Go, Python, C, Dart, Kotlin

Linux, Shell (Bash/Zsh), FTx, Git, Spring, Flutter, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Redis, MongoDB, Puppet, Docker, Distributed storage Miscellaneous

systems (EOS), distribute programming, desing patterns, design architectures

Soft Skills Time Management, teamwork, problem solving, communication, positive attitude, self-supervising, team leadership

Rome, Italy

Achievements

2019	3rd place , Local competitions of CyberChallenge 2019	Italy
2019	4th place, National competitions of CyberChallenge 2019	Italy
2018	Elite, Luca Raso scholarship for best students enrolled in Master's degree in Computer Engineering at Roma	Italv
	Tre University.	ituly
2016	Winner, Scholarship for best average grade in the Engineering Department of Roma Tre University.	Italy

Publications

Scaling blockchains without giving up decentralization and security: A solution to the blockchain scalability trilemma Gianmaria Del Monte, Diego Pennino, Maurizio Pizzonia

Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Cryptocurrencies and Blockchains for Distributed Systems, 2020

Conferences _____

C(ERN) BACK(UP): consolidated multi-petabyte backup solution for heterogenous storage and filesystems

Gianmaria Del Monte, Elizaveta Ragozina, Roberto Valverde Cameselle

CS3 2023 - Cloud Storage Synchronization and Sharing, 2023, https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/5207944

Applications integration beyond local clouds with OCM

Giuseppe Lo Presti, Gianmaria Del Monte, Michiel De Jong

 $CS3\,2023-Cloud\,Storage\,Synchronization\,and\,Sharing,\,2023, \\ \textbf{https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/5206694}$

Evolution of the CERN Backup system based on RESTIC and the CERN Tape Archive (CTA)

Fons Rademakers, Gianmaria Del Monte

26TH INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON COMPUTING IN HIGH ENERGY AND NUCLEAR PHYSICS - CHEP2023, 2023, https://indico.jlab.org/event/459/contributions/11294/

User-friendly OCM Invitation and Sharing: OCIS, CERNBox

Elizaveta Ragozina, Gianmaria Del Monte, Samuel Alfageme Sainz

CS3 2023 - Cloud Storage Synchronization and Sharing, 2023, https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/5208014

CERNBox backup evolution

Gianmaria Del Monte, Roberto Valverde Cameselle

6th EOS workshop, 2022, https://indico.cern.ch/event/1103358/contributions/4758282

Data safety in CERNBox

Gianmaria Del Monte

CERNBox User Forum, 2021, https://indico.cern.ch/event/1067354/contributions/4646494/

Visualizing physics data in ownCloud Infinite Scale

Gianmaria Del Monte

ownCloud Conference, 2021, https://cfp.owncloud.com/occon2021/talk/W8KHKM

Languages _

English Professional proficiency
Italian Native proficiency
French Basic knowledge